foreign
[Music]
ALK the internet radio broadcast for
lasers and holography enjoyed by
listeners throughout the world I'm Frank
defreitis and I'll be your host for each
installment bringing you news guests and
everything holographic now please enjoy
the latest show
please
[Music]
good morning Carmen it's Frank how are
you hello Frank how are you doing good
are you ready to do our interview uh
why don't we start off by having you
tell the listeners a little bit about
what it is you do there at the
University of Pennsylvania yeah I work
for the
for the um 10 years ago they brought
photodynamic therapy PDT
to UPenn
and so I've been working I was here and
then I left and then I came back a few
years ago so we've been doing cancer
research and also clinical treating
patients
patient with PDT
you know so I'm assuming this has
already passed the trials of using
whatever it is you use how do the trials
go
there's basic research with cells and
things like that and then if that shows
promise then they go into another phase
or they may use animals
or they go right to a clinical
patients so
really when we're talking about PDT
Frank we're talking about site-specific
treatments it's a die or something
that's absorbed by the cancer cells
um
well the dye is in the laser I see it's
a Dye Laser I see there is a chemical
it's a it's a drug that has been
developed that matches
it's a match with the wavelength of
light and the specific drug oh I see so
when they inject the drug or use it as a
cream depending on again where the
cancer is
you put the drug on
skin or
you know in the system and what happens
is
the cancer takes in more of the drug
than normal tissue
so it holds on to it longer so you wait
a little bit and that's all it developed
by according to the drug you wait a
little bit and then you can illuminate
excuse me eliminate with the laser
um the site where the cancer is
when the light hits the drug it creates
what they call a photochemical reaction
okay where it actually denatures the
cell the cancer cell and create singlet
oxygen
and the oxygen kills the cancer
because there's not a lot of drug left
in the normal tissue the normal tissue
that
it's not destroyed
so it's very promising when
um you don't want to be disfigured by
having it cut
a lot of cancer patients with
with for instance benefit because they
don't have all that surface cut off of
their skin you know a lot of times
people get it and it comes back and it
comes back
um
uh for instance it's FDA approved for
the esophagus for Barrett's esophagus
and
the alternative for some of these
patients is to have an esophagectomy
which means their whole esophagus has to
be removed
now with PDT
it it
works on the lining of the esophagus
kills that that
um
cancerous condition
pre-cancerous condition and then normal
tissue grows back
wow yeah so it's it's actually saving
people from a terrible terrible surgery
so if this really depends on
what cancer you're talking about we're
doing studies for lung
cancer uh we have studies in the
pipeline that we're going to start to do
but you know I can't really talk about
them because they haven't been approved
things like that but there's a lot of
work around the world in PDT
a lot of a lot of patients
patient Dermatology skin esophagus
if anybody's interested in this subject
go to oncolink on
okay
dot com
and that's the UPenn
cancer portal if you will it's a it's a
Clearinghouse of all kinds of
information but if you go into the
little search field and search PDT it'll
come up with all kinds of information
okay and it'll explain how it works
the laser the drug oxygen
obviously it doesn't work if there's no
Oxygen in a tissue
mm-hmm but um yeah it's a nice little
tutorial in there about it too and what
laser do you use to perform this we use
a it's
and it's the only one that was
originally FDA approved and that was
from laser scope it's a twin Crystal
KTP yag and that laser pumps
the die module laser which is a liquid
dye and that converts the energy to a
630 nanometer beam so we actually yeah
we do PDT in red
it's all red work that we do here
different wavelengths but uh primarily
red the wavelength is so close to helium
neon is it a power issue as far as the
reason why you wouldn't just use a
heenie uh yeah it is power
that as well as we need to make sure
that it's just it's monochromatic
communities aren't always monochromatic
there's a couple different lines of red
in there oh okay
so you know I mean
at 6 30 and that's the way that the the
drug company Works they they use a
specific wavelength there's a study
there's some work that's promising at
uh 665. it's all over the place but now
that we know that the that the body
allowing this
with the drug and the drug introduced
and then working with a matching
wavelength now that we know that I guess
a lot of people can go out and start to
really
you know study and research what other
wavelengths would be good you know what
tolerance does this drug have with
wavelengths is it specifically for 6 30
and 6 30 only uh the wavelength is
usually a peak
for that drug okay there's usually a
couple of peaks of absorption
there's a fluorescence Peak
but what we work at is usually at 6 30
plus or minus three nanometers okay uh
and it usually is a tolerance of plus or
minus three
because once you get away from what the
drug specifies then your your efficacy
your the efficiency of of the cell kill
goes down
and the point is to kill as much of it
as we can so obviously we would want to
work at the peak yeah yeah what is the
power of the beam that's being used uh
from the laser depending
we average like in the esophagus it's
usually one Watt
wow yeah one watt in a cylindrical
diffuser we use fiber optics to deliver
all this light uh
different types of fiber optics
one would be like I said this little
diffuser that's 360 degrees
um
because obviously if you picture it in
your mind the fiber is going down a
patient's throat
into the esophagus so there's a 360
degree field
that the light has to hit I see
um if you're working on the skin you
don't need something like that you just
need a homogeneous spot
so we use a fiber that has a little lens
on the end of it and that makes a nice
profile a nice beam profile yeah
so you know
a lot of this is you know what what
works who's doing what there's a lot of
collaboration with other associates
other
hospitals and medical centers
small community still but PDT is
definitely growing around the world yeah
getting back to the power you would
think that at one Watt
the beam would destroy just about any
living tissue that it would come in
contact with
that's not the case I assume no no but
there are benchmarks you know how much
power per centimeter Square we use what
is the total dosage and that's what the
studies
what's uh
what is the maximum we can dose
and what rate and what is the minimum
dose and what rate
that's all the we have real time to
assemble
cinematics people that come in
the light directly
in real time so we can tell that this
part of the tissue is getting this much
light you know let's go over to this
part of the tissue
and I know it sounds very science
fiction but uh the studies are written
to be very very specific of what is
allowed
you know what are we looking for what
are we trying to accomplish
sounds very basic science really that's
the foundation it is yeah it is and even
though PDT has been around for about
well I guess in
really in marketing terms have many have
been using it since the late 80s
but
there's not a lot of a lot of people
don't know about it because we just
don't know enough about it yet
lasers in medicine have been around for
many many years but PDT is different
because
in laser talk
now that uh
you know photothermal is when you kill
tissue with
okay where you actually create a burning
or quarterization
carbonize you know you're actually using
the beam to heat it up and this is not
what we're talking about here right
right now we're talking about a chemical
reaction that happens
so
you know yeah the light is is uh higher
power like one watt if I had a one watt
you know it's a power density issue if
it's in a very very small spot it's
going to burn you but if it's diffused
and spread out it's not going to hurt
you oh and that's how the treatment is
performed exactly oh I see so very
interesting more diffused yeah
yeah and that power drops very rapidly
once yeah
so uh it's just another way that we're
using light in the body
and and that's why I got into this
isn't a light freak well for the benefit
of those folks who would ever want to
consider making a jump over to working
with lasers professionally what was your
path leading you to this uh well
as a child as a kid I always was
interested in medicine but I was not
ready when I I went to the
photonics program at Camden County
College in Blackwood New Jersey
uh which is still there and it's still
quite an interesting program they've
added fiber optic degree with it
but I went there and when I was done I
realized that I just did not know enough
to work in the medical field because
there's a lot of responsibility with
that
you know and and pressure sometimes and
and you know you're dealing with
patience and human beings
so I went into another path I went into
manufacturing I learned how to build
them and just got a comfort level
years later after doing
kinds of work with lasers I ended up
back and got into the medical field with
a medical laser manufacturer I see and I
started working for them
and for 10 years actually
out of they were out of California and
that's the laser that was FDA approved
for PDT so that's how I got in to
University of Pennsylvania
well I got the perfect person to work
there
thanks
I uh but by then after all those years I
felt like
I I know the
the stand what's going on and I want to
make a difference so I
they offered me the job and I took it
took it but as a kid out of well
I'm quite a kid out of college but when
I got out it was like oh what would I do
I mean you know sometimes you have to
fix this
the laser you have to be on
of all the devices and all those things
and
I I wanted to go out and
do light shifts yeah I did what were
some of the other things you did with
lasers on your way to where you are now
well one was the
job that was in Long Island
quantronics
[Music]
after that I went to work with an outfit
that did laser light shows literally in
planetariums and I did that for a little
while okay
that was exciting that was fun
um and that really was the the gate that
told me that I can handle working on my
own okay because when you're doing shows
in plan ariums with
you know real live lasers real life
projection systems
the sound systems you know you're it you
have to be able to handle those things
you have to like it too
and uh so I did that for a little while
and as you and I had spoken before I
just kind of got bored with it actually
so that was my clue
that gee maybe I'm maybe I'm ready to do
something
that I've really been interested in all
my life I imagine there are a lot of
people that would love to do laser light
shows professionally how long did it
take you to become bored with it um
that
to be honest with you about four or five
months oh really
because
I want I wanted to
to be part of the programming I see I
wanted to say oh I'm listening to a
Beatles song and here's what I would
Envision at on the screen the creative
end yeah and I wasn't I was the azerist
so they were programmed
um on eight-track tape actually
is a very cool thing you know and I
enjoyed it don't get me wrong it's just
after a while I realized I'm not going
to be I'd have to do this for years
before I got into the studio to actually
be the creative end of it and do I want
to travel around and do this and
really just
to the show all the time you know you
add your little Flair and
um and I had a good time and they were
excellent shows that these people put
together
but like I said I always had the passion
for medicine
and so that's where it I had to just
follow that
until I got to where I was so after that
I went to that medical laser company
okay and started working for them
and traveling around and I'm and I know
for the laser
propeller heads is what my family calls
me
because I'm into it
but for all those out there there is
work but you do have to be willing to
travel most the time yeah I would like
to see more high-tech companies coming
to New Jersey
promote this
and they do slowly
your website's a great resource for
people to find out what's going on thank
you you expressed an interest in getting
involved with holography didn't you
that's another passion and that is just
because it's one of the coolest things
I've ever seen in my whole life you know
I don't even remember how I was a kid I
think one of the first ones I ever saw
and I thought my goodness I'd want to be
a part of that
so as soon as I found out that lasers
that I could study and be close to home
I dumped on it
and uh you know there's a lot of
hobbyists out there that if they wanted
to get serious and really
more technical stuff because the program
teaches you
all the interfacing like you'll have
computer courses Electronics different
set you know I'll be honest I wasn't
I I was one of three women in the whole
class okay and uh the three of us became
you know pretty good friends because we
had to help each other understand what
is he talking about
you know an Electronics class for
instance they would talk about
um
working on the car and use analogies of
you know starters and things like that
and we would look at each other and say
what is he talking
so
it was at that time it was very unusual
for women to be in this field now it's
not unusual at all yeah in fact around
the country I was called the laser lady
well maybe your show will actually
encourage other young women to look into
this as well if they're listening out
there that would be great it's a
wonderful opportunity and there's so
many different things you can
you can even holography is
non-destructive testing
uh Imaging you know I'd love to do well
you and I have talked about it just
different little projects and different
two Holograms of of uh
things that you don't normally see in
that way yeah you know
you could do close-ups you can do all
sorts of things and turn people on I
love teaching kids about this too you
know at your demonstration the other
week the kids were just so turned on by
it and it's
field
light is a tool
that is here to stay
the future it is certainly the future I
wish it was the present
well you know that's the hard part I I
know a lot of people that are interested
in this and they oh yeah it sounds great
but they don't really want to leave town
they don't want to work in other states
or so to those entrepreneurs out there I
really there's high-tech money for
startup companies there's got to be
somewhere you know what have an idea
what's your idea develop it and
New Jersey's got a whole lot of
Town New Jersey Pennsylvania
you know the tri-state area
most of the work is in California
Boston Austin Texas
Florida
you know so again if you want to live in
Florida there's work down there
it just depends on on what kind of life
you want to lead I I knew some of the
laserists who loved it they lived like
they were night owls because they did
all their shows at midnight 11 o'clock
at night
these guys were fabulous and they were
very creative a lot of them were
musicians and you know and I could see
the appeal and and it was very
it was a fun job but like I said I was
I knew there was something else for me
so that's why I'm here and quite happily
here
you're interested in the holographic
functioning of the brain as well aren't
you
one of the things that has been done
here at Penn
by the department of astronomy and
physics is that they've they're
profiling the human body and all all the
optical properties
and just recently there's a field called
plasmonics and that's Optical properties
of solid matter
we're talking about like hundreds of
years from now the Transporters from
Star Trek
you know how they they transport you
back and forth yes well they have to
know what the optical properties are
to be able of anything right I mean okay
if you were going to get into the Star
Trek analogy
well it's the old beam me up Scotty yeah
I'm familiar with that sure right well
there's also a book called the science
of Star Trek the physics of Star Trek it
tells you where and who was Richard
feyman
and whatever his name is I forget who
wrote it says small little paperback but
he gives you an idea of where we are
today presently
to have certain things like warp drive
Transporters and things like so that's
why I say to the listeners out there who
are Trek fans
very interesting book but back to the
what I was saying about Optical
properties
there's so much being done in that field
now and one is to look at the brain
and what's going on in the brain it's
not simply just electrical signals in a
linear path
and more and more evidence points to
more of a holographic a
three-dimensional way of knowing things
or way of creating memories
I don't know I mean I'm strictly an
amateur when it comes to this please
don't take me as you know the authority
but it's it's so interesting that I
would like to
and I would like to use what I know
to maybe image things to uh to look at
different ways of Imaging because you
can you
hologram of a picture
right yes so if you could do that of a
picture why couldn't you do it of an MRI
or of an x-ray
start to play with holographic Imaging
and see what happens but I know that uh
they're doing things right now
for instance not only just here but
they're using optical probes where they
send in and put in a beam of light
and look at the reflection
and the profile of the beam when it
comes back using spectroscopy
to actually see functions they can use
Optics now and and
to
follow blood flow the Dynamics of blood
flow all kinds of things so you know for
stroke victims and and brain damaged
victims there's all sorts of
possibilities because remember
if you can do something without cutting
or destroying tissue
that's what you want to do
[Music]
tool
so many different things that
ultimately you want to be able to
profile somebody's whole body again I go
back to Star Trek when they see the
tricorder the die Beverly she
will scan you
and and tell you where your problems are
oh you had a broken bone when you were
12 years old well how did she do that
well obviously a combination of Optics
and you know
something non-destructive
thing that will go through
skin penetrate tissue and give
information back I see and what does
that light does that hmm
so so you feel there's a great future in
medical imaging
it's with lasers Optics and such not oh
yeah and not only this Imaging but if
you you
always consider like part of the
electromagnetic spectrum part
that tool well you can weld steel you
can cut out a tumor
you can do a
share so many things with this tool it's
it's limited only by your imagination
and I'll tell you that's exactly what
the head of the laser program when I was
a student there
Fred sieber
that's exactly what he used to say to us
all the time you know we'd say well can
you do this and what about that and you
say
whatever your imagination can tell you
and now she have to learn how to make
that happen yes of course yeah so
because the internet is a great source
of information and there's a lot of
people doing
work that I'm talking about
just go out and look for it so you don't
have to repeat it now we can communicate
with each other and say hey you know
what don't waste your time I already did
that now let's try that and vibration is
now and
um
just all kinds of things even the fact
that you know you need a little you need
a little rig that you can put something
in it or gee where would I find that now
you go out online and
find almost anything you need yeah you
know as far as lab work and materials
and
the other thing another great place to
start if you're interested in the work
is in Material Science
Ceramics look at that 20 years ago
Ceramics weren't nearly what they are
now
ceramics
um
well they're talking about when you when
you were saying about holographic mind
holographic memory system I just read
this somewhere and excuse me if I get it
a little bit wrong but
if you were to put
they're looking at Crystals
store information
photo refractive crystals right
you can put so much information on the
on a crystal the size of your fingernail
that
you could probably get rid of you know
half the mainframes
in a building
they don't know why
but it's a Quantum effect
and it works so they're they're looking
at that yeah
so there's a lot of different things um
people are interested in lasers if
they're interested in holography look at
non-destructive testing
saves lives they've used it on jet
engines
they use it on a lot of things actually
nowadays
to make sure that there's no stress
fractures
you know
um my God 10 years ago if you had
wanted to know you know where else can I
use lasers they'd look at you and go
well there's a you know
scanners in the supermarket yes yes
but now you just have to look for it
[Music]
and and I think probably one of the most
noble things people could
field is the Young
teach our kids or at least get them
excited enough about it to pursue it
further you can give them all the facts
and figures in the world and if you
don't boost that interest and and get
them to have some sort of passion about
something it's just not going to take
place that's right these are things that
are possible without being afraid of all
the math believe me I am not a math
wizard
struggled and I remember days when I
throw my books across the room
and I'd go pick them up
sit back down and say okay you can do
this
you know
then again
it's just if you want to I I'm a firm
believer that if if you want something
bad enough and you work hard you'll get
it absolutely I believe that as well
yeah I mean look you've been in this
field for 20 years well a little more
than that yeah 23 years something like
that me too since 84. 83 for me yeah
so and and all those years I was away
from this work I
when working with lasers
for three years and I knew I had to go
back to it it was like one of those
Cosmic things
even if I had to just you know like
eventually like I said to you before I
want to do my own little Holograms at
home
um have my own they
video kind of thing easy enough to do
yeah well now with your help now that
I've you know
the yearbook is great
it's wonderful
thank you
I just took a sip of tea I'm sorry I
wasn't able to respond right away
but that uh that's shown me that even if
I
got away from this work for a little
while I could still
involved with light
yes
um you know and it's fun to play with
sunlight
you can use different Optics at your
window and light up a part of your room
that doesn't get much sunlight
fresnel lens and you know just play with
it
I don't know when but I'm definitely
going to sign up for one of your
workshops great love to have you come up
and hang out maybe
maybe swap some some technology and some
some skills we'll get you so that you
can go back to your house and start to
get your own Studio set up well and like
to do stainless
so incorporating the holographic plate
stained glass yes
there's always been something I wanted
to try so I'm getting close
okay
well Carmen we're coming close to the
end of our time is there anything that
we haven't talked about that you would
like to add to the program
into talking about
it if it's
if this has
enlightened anyone or given anybody an
idea to get into the work into this work
more power to you
I'm
if anybody has any questions if I can't
answer I usually can help them find the
answer that's wonderful but and if
anybody has anybody in their family or
themselves
I'd strongly recommend checking out that
oncolink website okay that's a wealth of
information too
all right well thank you Frank thank you
Carmen for taking the time to come on
the show and I'm sure the listeners
enjoyed what you had to say and found it
fascinating thank you again thanks
goodbye